Frances Rich Papers, 1912-1980
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Frances Rich papers
1912-1980
Rich, Frances
MS 129
5 boxes (2.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Sculptor; Director, Smith College Public Relations; and Officer, United States Naval Reserve, World War II. Focuses primarily on her career as a sculptor, with a small amount of material on her work (as student and staff) at Smith College and in U.S. Navy. Material includes correspondence, biographical articles, research files, clippings, exhibit catalogs (sculptures of notable people), posters, scrapbooks, and photographs.
Irene Frances Luther Rich was born in Spokane, Washington, on 8 January 1910. She was named after her mother, Irene Frances Luther (film actress Irene Rich), but used Frances Rich to avoid confusion. She was educated in Swiss schools and at the School for Girls in Santa Barbara, California. She received a B.A. from Smith College in 1931 with a major in English Literature.
In the years following her graduation, Rich appeared in a number of Hollywood films and on stage. In 1933 she met sculptor, Malvina Hoffman, and studied with her in Paris for two years. When she returned to the U.S. Rich did intensive work at the Boston Museum School and established her own studio in New York City. Between 1937 and 1940 she was a resident student at Cranbrook Academy of Art in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, where she met sculptor Carl Milles, with whom she worked for the next eighteen years.
When the United States entered World War II, Rich began work as a mechanical draftsman at Lockheed Aircraft in Burbank, California. In 1942 she joined the Women's Reserve of the U.S. Navy as a Junior Grade Lieutenant, graduating in the first class of women at the Officer's Training School at Smith College. She was posted to Washington, D.C. and became the National Director of Publicity for "V" Mail and traveling speaker for the Director of the WAVES. When she was discharged at the end of the war, Rich held the rank of Lt. Commander and received a citation for outstanding service from the Chief of Naval Personnel.
Following the war she did graduate work at Scripps College working with sculptor Albert Stewart, and at Columbia University. In 1947 she became the first Director of Public Relations at Smith College, a post she held until 1950 when she resigned to return to her art work. Rich has been featured in many publications and has exhibited in major art centers. Her works include portrait busts, wall and door panels, plaques and medallions, drawings, and statues. Subjects of her portrait busts include Alice Stone Blackwell, Lotte Lehmann, Margaret Sanger, Diego Rivera, and Katharine Hepburn. She also sculpted the Army-Navy Nurse Monument in Arlington National Cemetery in Washington, D.C. Much of her work is religious in nature and includes statues of St. Francis of Assisi, St. Joseph, Christ of the Sacred Heart, Our Lady of Combermere, St. Catherine of Siena, and various Madonnas. Rich established studios in California, and Payson, Arizona.
Frances Rich died at her home in Payson, Arizona, on October 14, 2007
The Frances Rich Papers focus primarily on her professional career as a sculptor, but include a small amount of material about her work as Public Relations Director at Smith College and her service in the U.S. Navy during World War II. The Papers are arranged in three series:
SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
SERIES II. ARTWORK
SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS
Types of material include correspondence, articles and clippings, memorabilia, photographs, exhibit catalogs, posters, and scrapbooks. Photographs are located in both SERIES II and III.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Frances Rich donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1981 to 1996. Priscilla Cunningham donated her letters from Rich in 2002. Additional materials were donated by Anthony Lame, son of Rich's college roommate, Mary Perkins Lame, in 2013.
Additional papers are housed at Cranbrook Academy of Art (Bloomfield Hills, Michigan), Getty Department of Humanities (Santa Monica, California), and Smith College Archives. In addition there nine of Rich's works of art located on the Smith College Campus (see Appendix I for locations). In 1982 Rich donated to the Sophia Smith Collection ten World War II WAVES recruitment posters. These are not part of the Frances Rich Papers and are located in the Sophia Smith Collection flat files.
Search Terms
Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950; Hepburn, Katharine, 1907-2003; Lehmann, Lotte; Rich, Frances; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966; Sculptors--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; United States. Naval Reserve. Women's Reserve--History--Sources; Women sculptors--United States--History--20th century--Sources
Appendix I
The following works of Frances Rich are located at Smith College:
Smith College Museum Bust: Laura Scales
Smith College Museum Bust: Diego Rivera
Smith College Museum Bust: Virgil Thompson
Smith College Museum Panel for bronze door of the Lew Wentz Mausoleaum, Ponca City, Oklahoma depicting the sports of baseball, basketball, and football
Smith College Museum Panel for bronze door of the Lew Wentz Mausoleaum, Ponca City, Oklahoma depicting the animals and their young
Smith College Museum Study for St. Francis
Smith College Museum Bas Relief for St. Peters Episcopal Church
Smith College Library Bust: Herbert Davis
Smith College Library Bust: Margaret Sanger
Center for the Performing Arts Bust: Katharine Hepburn as Cleopatra
Behind the President's House Statue: St. Francis of Assisi
Appendix II
Alphabetical list of works by Frances Rich
Alice Stone Blackwell, 1958-59
Army/Navy Nurse, Arlington National Cemetery, 1937
Birds in Flight, 1980
Carl Milles, 1971
Ch. King Eric v. Konigbach ("Little King"), 1946
Christ crucified, 1954
Christ of the Sacred Heart, 1972
Converse Colt, 1935
Crucifix, 1954
Diego Rivera, 1941
Earl Wild, 1976
Etruscan Rhythm, 1951
Everett Kimball, 1931
Harboe Nude, 1968
Healer, 1969
Jane and Little Billie, 1940
Katharine Hepburn, 1958, 1961
Laura Scales, 1936
Lew Wentz Mausoleum door, 1954
Little Emily, 1972
Look I'm Dancing, 1962
Lotte Lehmann, 1952
Madonna and Child, 1964
Madonna and Child, 1970
Margaret Sanger, 1956-57
Mother and Child (fountain figure), 1951
Mother and Child (seated), 1951
Mother and Child, 1956
Mother and Child, 1958
Mother and Child, 1958
Mother and Child, 1968
Negress, 1936
Our Lady of Combermere, 1960
Pelican, 1957
Pieta, 1953
Purdue University panel, 1939
Purification, 1958
Questing Madonna, 1954
Roadrunner, 1972
Seated Female Figure, 1958
Spirit of the Grape, 1976-77
St. Catherine of Sienna, 1968
St. Francis, 1951-71
St. Joseph, 1956
Taille Libre, 1936
Vanity, 1961
Virgil Thomson, 1961
Wailing Woman, 1951
Woman With Flower Pot, 1958
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1928-1970), .5 linear feet
  This series contains three subseries: Miscellaneous, Smith College, and U. S. Navy. The Miscellaneous material consists of clippings and articles (1931-77), an interview done by Mayne Ober Park for the Boston Globe in 1940, and two scrapbooks (1952-59) consisting primarily of clippings. In addition there is a small amount of correspondence. It consists of fourteen letters Rich wrote to Priscilla Cunningham (1979 -88), one letter from Irene Rich to Frances Snow (1931), two letters written to Frances Rich, and three third party letters about the possibility of granting Rich a Smith College Medal.
  The Smith College subseries contains printed material and memorabilia about Rich as a student, alumna, and as Director of Public Relations (1947-50). The latter also contains correspondence regarding the publication of This Is Smith College (1949).
  The U.S. Navy material includes correspondence and printed material related to Rich's service with the U. S. Navy Reserve (1942-48, 1980) and her training, particularly officer training at Smith College. There is also correspondence related to an oral history of Admiral Nimitz and the WAVES (1969-70).
  Photographs from these two subseries are located in SERIES III.
- SERIES II. ARTWORK (1931-1980), .75 linear feet
  This series is organized into two subseries: Works and Exhibitions. Works consists mostly of photographs of Rich's work, but also contains some related correspondence and printed material. It is arranged by date. (See Appendix II for an alphabetical list of these works.) Statues of the Army-Navy Nurses in Arlington National Cemetery, St Francis of Assisi, Our Lady of Combermere, St. Catherine of Siena, and the Spirit of the Grape; portrait busts of Lotte Lehmann, Diego Rivera, Margaret Sanger, and Katharine Hepburn; and drawings and photographs used for her work are represented in this subseries. Two copies of The Sculpture of Frances Rich by Merle Armitage (1974) are also included.
  The Exhibitions subseries includes photographs, correspondence, exhibit catalogs, articles and printed material. There is significant documentation of exhibitions at the Palm Springs Desert Museum (1969 and 1977) including two copies of The Sculpture of Frances Rich: Frances Rich Retrospective Exhibition, 7th February - 2nd March, 1969.
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS (1963-1988), .25 linear feet
  This series contains approximately seventy-five photographs, the bulk of which are photographs of Frances Rich alone (1914-77), with her mother Irene Rich, and with others. The latter include Laura Scales, Lottie Lehmann, Elissa Landi, Eugene Ormandy, John Ford, Diego Rivera, and Benjamin Wright. There are also photographs of Diego Rivera's fresco of Rich. In addition there are Smith College photographs from Rich's student years (1928-31), her tenure as Smith College Director of Public Relations (1947-50), and from her service with the U.S. Navy. Many of these are of her WAVES training at Smith College. There are also two photographs of Lotte Lehman, two of Irene Rich, and finally photographs of Rich's two California studio/homes: Hope and Shumway ranches (1941-68).
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Clippings, articles, and memorabilia, 1931-77, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview by Mayme Ober Park, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1952-64 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - To Priscilla Cunningham, 1979-88 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1931-58, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Smith College (Box 1)
    - Student (Box 1)
      - Scrapbook, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Articles, 1928-31, 1975-79 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Director of Public Relations (Box 1)
      - Articles and printed material, 1947-50, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - This Is Smith College: correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Navy (Box 1)
    - Clippings and articles, 1942-48, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Oral history of Admiral Nimitz and the WAVES: correspondence, 1969-70 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- SERIES II. ARTWORK
  - Works (Box 1)
    - General, 1931-77, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - Laura Scales, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Army/Navy Nurse, Arlington National Cemetery, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Diego Rivera, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - St. Francis of Assisi (Box 2)
      - Photographs, 1951-71 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Clippings, articles, and printed materials, 1952-66 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Lotte Lehmann, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Questing Madonna, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - St. Joseph, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Margaret Sanger, 1956-57 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Pelican, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Seated female figure, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Alice Stone Blackwell, 1958-59 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Katharine Hepburn, 1958, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Our Lady of Combermere, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - St. Catherine of Sienna, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Roadrunner, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Spirit of the Grape, 1976-77 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Birds in Flight, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photographs containing more than one work or unidentified works, 1977-78, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Drawings, 1944-46, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Sculpture of Frances Rich by Merle Armitage, 1974 (two copies, both autographed) (Box 3)
  - Exhibitions (Box 3)
    - California Palace of the Legion of Honor, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Palm Springs Desert Museum (Box 3)
      - Frances Rich Retrospective Exhibition, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Frances Rich Sculpture Show, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous, 1963-75 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Catalogs, 1952-73 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Rich, Frances (Box 3)
    - Alone, 1914-77 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - With others, 1937-72, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - With Irene Rich, circa 1912-46, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Smith College (Box 4)
    - Student, 1928-31 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Director of Public Relations, 1947-50 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Navy, 1941-47, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Lehmann, Lotte, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Rich, Irene, circa 1941 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Studios: Hope and Shumway Ranches, 1941-68, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- SERIES IV. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Sculpture of Margaret Sanger's head, and clipping, undated (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Spirit of the Grape undated (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Birds in Flight, undated (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Jane, Frances, and Irene Rich, 1927 (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Frances and Irene Rich, circa 1942 (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Vice Admiral Morris Denfeldt,undated (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
  - Certificate from the American Bicentennial Research Institute, 1974 (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
  - Shumway Ranch, Palm Desert, California (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Plans for studio and caretakers cottage (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Bureau of Land Management map (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
  - Posters (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - St. Francis of Asissi (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Spirit of the Grape (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Seated Woman with Child (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)
    - Harboe Nude (Map-case Flat File dwr 33)